{"tossups": [{"question": "In The Philosophy of Symbolic Forms, Ernst Cassirer argued that this concept is a symbolic form characterized by an absence of \"representational function,\" so that the name of a thing is the thing itself. In a series of debates, Rudolf Bultmann's distinction between this concept and the kerygma (keh-RIG-mah), or \"proclamation,\" was challenged by Karl Jaspers (YAH-\"spurs\"). In Dialectic of Enlightenment, Theodor Adorno argues that this concept already is Enlightenment, and Enlightenment inevitably returns to this concept. In Re lections on Violence, Georges Sorel (ZHORZH \"so\"-REL) argues that the \"social\" variant of this concept, rather than dialectical materialism, is the foundation for the \"general strike.\" The \"Spindle of Necessity\" assigns souls to their next lives in a passage commonly named for this type of construct that appears at the end of Plato's Republic. Religious scholar Mircea Eliade (MEER-\"chia\" ell-ee-AH-day) argues that participation in this construct allows for the \"eternal return.\" For 10 points, give this term for an archetypal story, such as those of Oedipus and Sisyphus.", "answer": "mythology [prompt on stories or legends]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "The \"reverse\" form of this effect results in loss of stromal ca\u00b7ve\u00b7olin-1 and autophagy of neighboring  broblasts. In one type of tissue this effect occurs when the E\u00b73 ligase von Hippel-Lindau protein can no longer interact with hypoxia-inducible factor one-alpha. Lloyd Demetrius attributed the age-dependent acceleration of brain dysfunction in Alzheimer's and Parkinson's to the the \"inverse\" form of this effect. Di\u00b7chloro\u00b7acetic acid inhibits this effect by inhibiting mono\u00b7carboxylate transporters. It is o ten accompanied by an increase in the PK-M2 isoform of pyruvate kinase. This effect is the reverse of the Pasteur effect. The idea for this effect was based on the observation that certain types of tumors produce lactate even in the presence of oxygen. For 10 points, give this effect named for a German doctor who observed that cancer cells rely mostly on glycolysis.", "answer": "Warburg effect", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This poem describes a person who will \"fit his tongue to dialogues of business, love, or strife...as if his whole vocation were endless imitation.\" Harold Bloom argued that this poem set the template for the \"crisis-lyric\" followed by poets as diverse as Whitman, Dickinson, and Stevens. The most dramatic turn in this poem occurs after the speaker predicts a time when \"custom [will] lie upon thee with a weight, heavy as frost, and deep almost as life!\" Uncharacteristically for its author, this poem uses a Platonic metaphor in the stanza beginning \"Our birth is but a sleep and a forgetting.\" The first four stanzas of this poem, which ask \"Whither is fled the visionary gleam?\", prompted a response from Coleridge in \"Dejection: An Ode.\" This poem concludes, \"to me the meanest flower that blows can give thoughts that do o ten lie too deep for tears.\" For 10 points, name this irregular Pindaric ode by William Wordsworth.", "answer": "\"Ode: Intimations of Immortality from Recollections of Early Childhood\" [or the Intimations Ode; or the Immortality Ode; or the Great Ode]", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A ter proclaiming his hatred of Nature's indi1\u20442ference, this character complains that personal death has been replaced by \"an anonymous cheapened death which we could dole out to entire nations on a mathematical basis.\" He argues that \"before deciding what is wrong and what is right we must  rst  nd out what we are,\" illustrating his point with a story about how his cultured tailor recently swallowed the beating heart of a man from Switzerland. This character says he learned \"this is a world of bodies\" during a period of imprisonment when he discovered that the \"cells of the inner self are worse than the deepest stone dungeon.\" He recalls how he vomited at the sacking of a Carmelite convent in a speech punctuated by his asthmatic gasps as he is whipped. At the end of the play, he stands on his chair and laughs triumphantly as Coulmier (\"COOL\"-myay) orders the nurses to brutally beat the asylum inmates. For 10 points, name this man who stages the assassination of Jean-Paul Marat in a play by Peter Weiss (\"VICE\").", "answer": "the Marquis de Sade [or Donatien Alphonse Franc\u0327ois de Sade]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. In 1966, John Gerassi argued that an oligarchical power play was behind a conspiracy exploiting this attitude during which town hall speeches were given by John L. Butler and future senator Frank Church. This attitude intensi ed in 1960 a ter the defection of two NSA codebreakers to the Soviet Union. During the election of 1964, the Barry Goldwater campaign exploited this attitude by making allusions to the Walter Jenkins incident. This attitude is why Clayton Hartwig was blamed for the 1989 explosion of the USS Iowa, and erupted in Boise a ter the Idaho Statesman published the headline \"Crush the Monster.\" Dwight Eisenhower's Executive Order 10450 instituted civil service  rings based on this prejudice, which Richard Nixon expressed in a conversation featuring the exchange \"Hot pants. Jesus Christ.\" This attitude motivated the delivery of \"blue discharges\" during World War II and witch hunts of o1\u20442 cials during the \"lavender scare.\" For 10 points, identify this attitude of suspicion whose prevalence in the military spurred the passage of \"Don't Ask, Don't Tell.\"", "answer": "homophobia [or anything involving fear of gay people, or fear of sexual deviance, or fear that gay people might be communists; or the Lavender Scare; prompt on the Red Scare or fear of Communists which is related]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This university commissioned Helmut Jahn to design a dormitory that is clad in corrugated steel and divided into six segments. Its chapel, which is built of white masonry except for a large ground-to-roof glass panel in its front, is nicknamed \"the God Box\" by students. Its School of Architecture is housed in a building composed of one massive room uninterrupted by any internal supports and surrounded on all sides by glass windows encased in black steel beams. Rem Koolhaas designed a massive stainless steel tube to shield this university's student center from noise pollution from an elevated train that runs through its campus. The site of Crown Hall, in the 1940s and 50s, this university was redesigned according to the master plan of its Dean of Architecture, Ludwig Mies van der Rohe. For 10 points, name this Chicago university.", "answer": "Illinois Institute of Technology [or IIT; or Illinois Tech]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The poem \"To Return to the Trees\" concludes with the image of an \"obdurate almond going under the sand with [one of these things], slowly, by sand grains, by centuries.\" The penultimate poem of the sequence Midsummer ends by describing one of these things that \"had winged lions in it, and birds cut into a wall.\" The speaker of the poem \"Codicil\" claims that \"to change [this thing] you must change your life.\" The speaker of another poem describes how the sprinkling from \"an earthen, water-bearing vessel\" turns him and his countrymen into \"good Fridays\" who make their master's one of these things their own. The speaker asks, \"how choose between this Africa and [one of these things] I love?\" in \"A Far Cry from Africa.\" For 10 points, name these things, the choice of which is an issue for post-colonial writers such as Derek Walcott, who primarily used the English one to compose his works.", "answer": "languages [or tongues]", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Perturbative expansion of one type of this system in terms of two coupling constants with a  xed ratio produces an equation of motion where the second time derivative of the more slowly changing variable is proportional to the partial derivative of an e1\u20442fective potential with respect to that variable. David Acheson derived the conditions under which another type of this system may be coupled to itself an arbitrary number of times while remaining stable. The Furuta type of this system is a benchmark for testing nonlinear control strategies for under-actuated mechanical devices. The exact solution for the simplest type of this system contains a complete elliptic integral of the  rst kind. The equation \"three cosine theta-one\" plus \"sine theta-two\" equals \"two\" de nes the onset of chaotic behavior in the \"double\" type of this system. For 10 points, name this oscillatory system in which a mass is suspended from a pivot.", "answer": "pendulums [accept Kapitza pendulum, inverted pendulum, Furuta pendulum, or double pendulum; prompt on parametric oscillators or driven harmonic oscillators; do not accept \"simple harmonic oscillators\"]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This food, which pejoratively gave its name to Taiwan's millennial generation, was reclaimed as a badge of honor a ter a 2008 student protest. It was the namesake of the printing press that printed Thomas Gray's two Pindaric odes and which is generally credited as the  rst private press in England. Captain Queeg theorizes that a duplicate key was forged during his inquest into the the t of a quart of this food in The Caine Mutiny. In Othello, Desdemona's handkerchief is embroidered with this food. The aforementioned private printing press was run by Horace Walpole from his famed Gothic revival mansion, which was also named for this food. An aging doctor remembers gathering this fruit with his childhood sweetheart Sara in a  lm in which he and his daughter pick up hitchhikers as they travel across Sweden for an award ceremony. For 10 points, name this fruit, \"wild\" examples of which title an Ingmar Bergman  lm.", "answer": "wild strawberry", "subcategory": "Other Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This political party was a1\u20442 liated with the militant BTI, which launched \"unilateral action\" against landlords. An extremist faction of this party pursued the \"Gottwald Plan,\" which was discredited a ter sparking the Madiun A1\u20442fair. Images of this political party's associated women's group performing the hypersexualized \"Fragrant Flower Dance\" before committing murder can still be found in a museum at the \"Crocodile's Pit.\" This party's members were targeted by the Ansor militia during an event in which they were linked with the \"Gestapu\" and the U.S. Embassy handed out lists of thousands of its members. The Washington Post-leaked \"Cornell Paper\" argued that this party was not responsible for the killing of six generals during an attempted coup. Joshua Oppenheimer's documentary The Act of Killing describes how this party was blamed for the 30th September Movement, leading to a gangster-led purge of up to a million citizens. For 10 points, name this party for peasants and workers that was liquidated by death squads with the blessing of Suharto.", "answer": "Indonesian Communist Party [prompt on partial answer; accept the PKI or Partai Komunis Indonesia]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A 1987 paper found negative consequences from this phenomenon by creating the  rst formalization of the Roy Model. A 2016 paper on this phenomenon by Giovanni Peri drew criticism for equating high school dropouts with workers still in high school. Rachel Friedberg studied the collapse of the Soviet Union to produce a classic paper on this phenomenon, which has been blamed for a legion of social evils, including black-on-black crime, by Harvard economist George Borjas. It's not the minimum wage, but in 2015, Borjas questioned David Card's 1990 study that modeled this phenomenon as a \"supply shock\" with data from Miami. Charles Kenny found that 26% of all startups and patents result from this phenomenon, which may displace skilled workers through the use of \"H1-B\" status. For 10 points, identify this phenomenon whose supposed adverse economic e1\u20442fects would theoretically be curbed by Donald Trump's wall.", "answer": "immigration [or immigration to the United States; or illegal immigration]", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "The strongest textual evidence for this religious belief is in First Corinthians 3:11, which describes building on Christ's foundation with gold, silver, or wood. The widespread translation of a text about the knight Tundale collapsing was a landmark in the history of this belief, according to Annales School historian Jacques le Go1\u20442f, who traced its birth to the 12th century. As this belief spread, more pilgrims visited a cave on Station Island in Lough Derg (lo f derg) where St. Patrick met Jesus. Stephen Greenblatt analyzed the in\u0500luence of the abolition of this idea on Shakespeare's Hamlet. This belief led donors in England to found 800 \"chantries\" where priests sung masses. Johann Tetzel alluded to this belief in a jingle that raised money for St. Peter's Basilica, because believers in it bought \"indulgences\" for dead relatives. For 10 points, name this Catholic belief in a liminal territory that puri es souls before they enter Heaven.", "answer": "Purgatory [or Purgatorium]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A normal example of these sequences has an underlying sigma field equal to sigma of the sign of the W function; that one named for Azema is subject to Kurtz\u2019s theorem, which states that one of these things converges if the \u201cZ-hat t\u201d operator for it is self-adjoint. Certain \u201ccadlag\u201d sequences can be decomposed into one of these sequences and an \u201cincreasing predictive process\u201d by the Doob-Meyer theorem. Both these sequences and their \u201csuper-\u201d generalization are defined over filtrations, but in the latter the equals operator has been replaced with a \u201cgreater than or equal to\u201d operator in the definition of EV. An 18th-century strategy in which one repeatedly doubles their bets gives its name to these processes, an example of which is a finite-dimensional random walk. For 10 points, name these sequences of random variables in which the expected value of one variable equals the observed value of the one previous to it, regardless of other prior observations.", "answer": "martingales", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This character addresses the \"dark Hindoo half of nature\" as he watches an animal turn to \"seek intercedings with yon all-quickening sun\" before it dies. In a soliloquy, this character compares his followers to revolving wheels within his \"cogged circle,\" then to \"so many ant-hills of powder...and I their match,\" and describes himself as \"madness maddened: that wild madness that's only calm to comprehend itself.\" This character boasts, \"I'd strike the sun if it insulted me,\" a ter remarking of his enemy, \"He tasks me; he heaps me; I see in him outrageous strength, with an inscrutable malice sinewing it.\" This character exclaims \"to the last I grapple with thee; from hell's heart I stab at thee\" just before he is caught by a rope and killed by the creature that tore o1\u20442f his leg years before. For 10 points, name this captain of the Pequod who hunts the title whale in Moby-Dick.", "answer": "Captain Ahab", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Otto Skorzeny trained the \"Black Cats\" unit to  ght for the Nazis in this modern-day country. The worst war criminal  ghting in this constituent country was Oskar Dirlewanger, the drug-addled leader of a brigade of convicted poachers that burnt civilians alive as part of a larger plan to purge its capital and rebuild it as an Aryan colony called \"Asgard.\" General Platon coordinated actions with a group of Naliboki Forest partisans in this modern-day country made up of 1200 Jews under the Bielski Brothers. In 1943, the Nazi commissar over this country, Wilhelm Kube (koo-beh), was killed by a time bomb planted by a partisan working as his maid. In 1988, Zyanon Paznyak exhumed mass graves containing up to 200,000 purge victims in this country's Kurapaty Forest. Timothy Snyder's Bloodlands argues that the most horri c interactions between Nazism and Stalinism happened in this country, which lost a third of its population and two-thirds of its cities in World War II. For 10 points, name this country where Soviet atrocities are denied by the government of Alexander Lukashenko.", "answer": "Belarus", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Note to players: artist and type of work required. In one of these paintings, the word \"ADONAI\" is inscribed on St. George's breastplate as he introduces the title jowly canon, whose salvation is signi ed by armrest sculptures of Cain killing Abel and Samson wrenching a lion's jaws apart. Two angels unfurl a cloth canopy in one of these paintings set \"at the Fountain,\" and the subject towers halfway up to the ceiling of a Gothic cathedral in one of them set \"in the Church.\" The most famous painting from this set represents the seven deadly sins through stone rabbits underneath a column, four capitals depicting Bible stories, idlers on a battlement, and the title character's gold-studded belt. That painting's foreground features a room tiled with eight-pointed stars where an angel holds a giant crown above the head of the title character. For 10 points, name this group of paintings of the Holy Mother, including one painted for Chancellor Rolin, by the artist of the Ghent Altarpiece.", "answer": "Madonnas by Jan van Eyck", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Electrons in e-sub-g orbitals do not contribute to orbital angular momentum because the e-sub-g orbitals cannot transform between each other under this operation. Irreducible representations are labelled B if they have a character of -1 for this operation. Like EPR transitions, transitions of this type tend to have single wavenumber energies. FT-IR can resolve peaks with identical spacing that appear due to this type of transition, which are responsible for forming the P and R branches. In Schoen\u0500lies (SHUN-\" lees\") notation, \"improper\" versions of this operation are denoted S, while \"proper\" n-fold symmetries under this operation are denoted C-sub-n. Linear molecules only have two degrees of freedom under this operation, while non-linear molecules have three. For 10 points, circles have an in nite amount of what type of symmetry that involves moving a point a certain number of degrees about an axis?", "answer": "rotation [or word forms such as rotational]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This character's death is indirectly caused by one of his sons pretending to be a pregnant woman in front of a group of sages. When this character places a child with three eyes and four arms on his lap, the extra appendages disappear. This character's kinsmen kill each other en masse with blades of grass that turn into iron clubs, ful lling a curse placed on him by another character who states that the women of his race will weep just as she has wept for her one hundred dead sons. While waiting for this character to wake up, Duryodhana (dur-yohd-HAH-nah) arrogantly sits behind his head rather than at his feet; as a result, this character's armies  ght for the Kauravas, but he personally serves as an advisor to the Pandavas. This character says \"I am become death, the destroyer of worlds\" in a speech on the importance of following dharma. For 10 points, name this character in the Mahabharata who acts as Arjuna's charioteer and is an avatar of Vishnu.", "answer": "Krishna [prompt on Vishnu]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "One form of this resource was governed by the precarium, a type of law derived from the word preces meaning \"request.\" During a war fought over this resource, slingers inscribed their bullets with still-extant gra1\u20442 ti about Fulvia's vagina. Octavian and Antony fought the Perusine War over the distribution of this resource, which Pompey used in order to buy o1\u20442f the pirates he claimed to have defeated. In addition to allowing plebeians to access the consulship, the 4th-century Licinio-Sextian laws regulated the purchase of this resource. The Lex Sempronia  nanced the collegia distributing this resource with the Roman people's inheritance from Attalus III of Pergamum; that reform sought to end the dispossession of Roman soldiers abroad through its concentration into slave-run latifundia that exceeded 500 iugera (YOO-ger-uh). For 10 points, name this factor of production whose inequities provoked the con\u0500lict between the Senatorial class and the Gracchi, who championed the cause of smallholding farmers.", "answer": "land [or Roman farmland]", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A \"multiple\" variant of this instrument was designed for Benjamin Britten's church parable The Burning Fiery Furnace, in\u0500luenced by a Japanese instrument called the shakubyoshi (SHAH-koo-BYOH-shee). A pair of notes played by this instrument marks the transition between the \"Malaguen\u0303a\" (mah-lah-GWAY-nyah) and \"Loreley\" movements of Dmitri Shostakovich's fourteenth symphony. Krzysztof Penderecki's  rst symphony opens with a solo for this instrument in which it plays a series of individual notes separated by pauses. In Mahler's   th symphony, this instrument appears only in the scherzo, in which the trumpets double it when it twice takes over the rhythm from the glockenspiel. Maurice Ravel's Piano Concerto in G Major begins with a single note played by this instrument. For 10 points, name this percussion instrument consisting of two pieces of wood joined by a hinge, which imitates the characteristic \"crack\" of its namesake tool.", "answer": "whip [or slapstick; or clapper; or Holzklapper]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "During the late 19th century, one of these places in Telz adopted many innovations inspired by the principles of the Musar Movement. During the 20th century, the majority of these places adopted the Brisker method, whose six steps include clarifying and classifying basic concepts. Medieval ones focused on the delivery of a hiluk using the method of pilpul at the end of a period of time called a zeman. In the United States, many of these places are divided into institutions called the ketana, the mesivta, and the kollel. The  rst modern example of one of these places was founded in Volozhin in 1803 by a student of the Gaon of Vilna. In Israel, many ultra-Orthodox Jews receive welfare so they can spend time in these places instead of working. For 10 points, name these schools where Jews study the Torah and the Talmud.", "answer": "yeshivas [or yeshivot; prompt on school or Jewish school or similar answers; do not accept or prompt on \"shul\"]", "category": "Religion"}], "bonuses": []}